"Adrenal Fatigue: What It Is and How to Treat It"
Many seeking treatment
for common nonspecific symptoms
are led to believe
they are suffering
from some sort
of hormonal deficiency.
"Adrenal fatigue"
is the prototypical example.
Chiropractor-coined in 1998,
the invented diagnosis
has since been embraced
by naturopaths,
functional medicine,
and anti-aging doctors.
But does adrenal fatigue
even exist?
The alleged condition is said
to result from chronic stress
leading to an "overuse"
of the adrenal glands
and their eventual
functional decline.
Symptoms supposedly include
fatigue, body aches,
sleep issues,
and digestive problems,
at least
according to the websites
not so coincidentally selling
a suite of supplements
to remedy it.
It will come as no surprise
that the originator
of the term
sells supplements
on his website
to treat it
for $200 a month.
But it may not be
an actual medical condition.
The symptoms people have
are real,
but they just may be caused
by something else,
for example, sleep apnea,
chronic fatigue syndrome,
or fibromyalgia.
Saliva tests for adrenal
hormone levels are not reliable,
with studies showing so-called
"adrenal fatigue" patients
having higher levels
than controls,
similar levels,
or lower levels,
"an almost systematic finding
of conflicting results."
There is an actual disease
of adrenal insufficiency
known as Addison's disease,
which is diagnosed
with an ACTH stimulation test.
You inject people with
adrenocorticotropic hormone,
the signal your brain uses
to get your adrenal glands
to pump out
the stress hormone cortisol,
and if your adrenals
don't respond,
that shows your adrenal glands
must be in trouble.
But inject those
presumed to be suffering
from chronic stress and fatigue
with ACTH
and sometimes you even get
a greater rise in cortisol,
disproving the notion
that stress causes
the adrenals to "burn out."
But wait,
you were diagnosed with "AF,"
given corticosteroids,
and now you feel great,
so it must have been real.
That's the thing
about corticosteroids, though.
One of the side effects is
a euphoric sense of well-being.
The problem is
that even low doses
can increase the risk
of osteoporosis,
psychiatric and metabolic
disorders, muscle damage,
glaucoma, sleep disturbances,
and cardiovascular diseases.
But wait, you took some
"adrenal support" supplements,
checked the labels,
confirmed they don't have
any hormones,
and still felt better.
They lie.
Researchers checked the 12 most
popular adrenal support supplements,
and every single one
contained hidden hormones,
none of which were declared
on the product labels.
All contained thyroid hormone
and most a steroid hormone
as well,
pregnenolone, budesonide,
androstenedione, progesterone,
cortisone, or cortisol.
Adrenal fatigue reminds me
of what used to be called
"electromagnetic
hypersensitivity,"
now referred to
in the medical literature
as "idiopathic
environmental intolerance
attributed to
electromagnetic fields,"
unspecific symptoms
supposedly triggered
by things like cell phones.
There have been
at least 46 studies
involving more than 1,000 people
that claim to be affected,
yet when put to the test
in blinded trials
the studies
near universally failed
to show that anyone
could even detect the fields.
Why don't journalists covering
these stories mention the data?
Because there are
snake-oil salesmen
profiting off
the perceived condition,
selling all matter of
so-called "protective" gadgets
that viciously attack anyone
even daring to mention
the science,
accusing them
of denying the reality
of people's symptoms.
But it's arguably the opposite.
They are the ones
hindering sufferers
from getting to the bottom
of what is actually causing
their symptoms.
Similarly, hawking
unproven tests and treatments
for adrenal fatigue
could delay the diagnosis
of a real, treatable condition.